export const JambBiology = [
  {
    question: "Which of the following characterizes a mature plant cell?",
    options: [
      "The cytoplasm fills up the entire cell space",
      "The nucleus is pushed to the centre of the cell",
      "The cell wall is made up of cellulose",
      "The nucleus is small and irregular in shape",
    ],
    answer: "The cell wall is made up of cellulose",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is NOT a function of the nucleus of a cell?",
    options: [
      "It controls the life processes of the cell",
      "It translates genetic information for the manufacture of proteins",
      "It stores and carries hereditary information",
      "It is reservoir of energy for the cell",
    ],
    answer: "It is reservoir of energy for the cell",
  },
  {
    question: "The dominant phase in the life cycle of a fern is the?",
    options: ["Gametophyte", "Prothallus", "Sporophyte", "Antheridium"],
    answer: "Sporophyte",
  },
  {
    question: "Parental care is exhibited by",
    options: ["Toads", "Snails", "Earthworms", "Birds"],
    answer: "Birds",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is lacking in the diet of a person with kwashiorkor?",
    options: ["Vitamins", "Proteins", "Carbohydrates"],
    answer: "Proteins",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The mode of nutrition of sundew and bladderwort can be described as",
    options: ["Autotrophic", "Saprophytic", "Holozoic", "Chemosynthetic"],
    answer: "Holozoic",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When the mixture of a food substance and Benedict's solution was warmed, the solution changed from blue to black-red. This indicates the presence of",
    options: ["Reducing sugar", "Fatty acid", "Sucrose", "Amino acid"],
    answer: "Reducing sugar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The primary structure responsible for pumping blood for circulation through the mammalian circulatory systems is the",
    options: ["Veins", "Right auricle", "Arteries", "Left ventricle"],
    answer: "Left ventricle",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Circulation of blood to all parts of the body except the lungs is through",
    options: [
      "The pulmonary artery",
      "Systemic circulation",
      "The lymphatic system",
      "Pulmonary circulation",
    ],
    answer: "Systemic circulation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Yeast respires anaerobically to convert simple sugar to carbon (IV) oxide and",
    options: ["Alcohol", "Acid", "Oxygen", "Water"],
    answer: "Alcohol",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The sheet of muscle that separates the thoracic and the abdominal cavities is the",
    options: [
      "Diaphragm",
      "Intercostal muscle",
      "Pleural membrane",
      "Pericardium",
    ],
    answer: "Diaphragm",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The oily substance that lubricates the mammalian hair to keep it flexible and water repellent is secreted by the",
    options: [
      "Sweat glands",
      "Sebaceous glands",
      "Fatty cells",
      "Granular layer",
    ],
    answer: "Sebaceous glands",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The outer layer of the kidney where the Bowman's capsules are found is the",
    options: ["Cortex", "Pelvis", "Medulla", "Pyramid"],
    answer: "Cortex",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following stimuli is likely to elicit a nastic response in an organism?",
    options: ["Touch", "Light intensity", "Chemical substances", "Gravity"],
    answer: "Chemical substances",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the male reproductive system of a mammal, sperm is stored in the",
    options: ["Van deferens", "Urethra", "Epididymis", "Seminiferous tubules"],
    answer: "Epididymis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Chemosynthetic organisms are capable of manufacturing their food from simple inorganic substances through the process of",
    options: ["Oxidation", "Denitrification", "Reduction", "Phosphorylation"],
    answer: "Phosphorylation",
  },
  {
    question: "The part of the human gut that has an acidic content is the",
    options: ["Stomach", "Duodenum", "Ileum", "Colon"],
    answer: "Stomach",
  },
  {
    question:
      "I. Stomata → Spirogyro II. Alveoli → Earthworm III. Malpighian tubule → Mammal IV. Contractile vacuole → Protozoa. Which of the above structures is correctly matched with the organisms in which it is found?",
    options: ["III", "II", "I", "IV"],
    answer: "IV",
  },
  {
    question: "A food chain always begins with a",
    options: ["Consumer", "Decomposer", "Producer", "Primary consumer"],
    answer: "Producer",
  },
  {
    question: "Mycorrhizae promote plant growth by",
    options: [
      "Absorbing inorganic ions from the soil",
      "Protecting it from infection",
      "Helping it to utilize atmospheric nitrogen",
      "Serving as a growth regulator",
    ],
    answer: "Absorbing inorganic ions from the soil",
  },
  {
    question: "The barrier between maternal and foetal blood is the",
    options: ["Placenta", "Liver", "Umbilical chord", "Uterine wall"],
    answer: "Placenta",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The blood component that has the greatest affinity for oxygen is the",
    options: ["Lymphocytes", "Leucocytes", "Erythrocytes", "Thrombocytes"],
    answer: "Erythrocytes",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following organisms is mainly found in the marine habitat?",
    options: ["Achatina", "Tilapia", "Dog fish", "Tortoise"],
    answer: "Dog fish",
  },
  {
    question: "The two halves of the pelvic girdle are joined together at the",
    options: ["Public symphysis", "Ilium", "Pubis", "Obturator foramen"],
    answer: "Public symphysis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "I. Adoption of appropriate nocturnal habits II. Burrowing III. Adjusting their internal body temperature. IV. Possession of many sweat pores. Which of the above are ways in which desert animals adapt to extreme heat of the environment?",
    options: [
      "I and IV only",
      "II and III only",
      "I and II only",
      "I, II and III only",
    ],
    answer: "I and II only",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Low annual rainfall, sparse vegetation, high diurnal temperatures and cold nights are characteristic features of the",
    options: [
      "Tropical rainforest",
      "Desert",
      "Montane forest",
      "Guinea savanna",
    ],
    answer: "Guinea savanna",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The activity of an organism which affects the survival of another organism in the same habitat constitutes",
    options: [
      "An edaphic factor",
      "An abiotic factor",
      "A biotic factor",
      "A physiographic factor",
    ],
    answer: "An edaphic factor",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The average number of individuals of species per unit area of the habitat is the",
    options: [
      "Population density",
      "Population frequency",
      "Population size",
      "Population distribution",
    ],
    answer: "Population size",
  },
  {
    question: "The vector for yellow fever is",
    options: ["Aedes mosquito", "Anopheles mosquito", "Tsetse fly", "Blackfly"],
    answer: "Anopheles mosquito",
  },
  {
    question: "The loss of soil through erosion can be reduced by",
    options: ["Watering", "Crop rotation", "Manuring", "Irrigation"],
    answer: "Watering",
  },
  {
    question: "The protozoan Plasmodium falciparum is transmitted by",
    options: [
      "Female Anopheles mosquitoes",
      "Female Aedes mosquitoes",
      "Female Culex mosquitoes",
      "Female blackfly",
    ],
    answer: "Female Anopheles mosquitoes",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The theory that new organs or characteristics develop in organisms when there is a need for them was postulated by",
    options: ["Mendel", "Darwin", "Lamarck", "De Vries"],
    answer: "Lamarck",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The relationship between a whale and barnacles growing on its back is known as",
    options: ["Parasitism", "Symbiosis", "Predation", "Commensalism"],
    answer: "Commensalism",
  },
  {
    question: "The function of the red head in male Agama lizards is to",
    options: [
      "conceal and camouflage the animal from predators",
      "scare other males from the territory",
      "attract female lizards for mating purposes",
      "warn predators of the distastefulness of the animal",
    ],
    answer: "attract female lizards for mating purposes",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which of the following species is the biomass of an individual the smallest?",
    options: [
      "Agama sp.",
      "Bufo sp.",
      "Tracheophytes and ferns",
      "Angiosperms and gymnosperms",
    ],
    answer: "Thallophytes and bryophytes",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which of the following groups of vertebrates is parental care mostly exhibited?",
    options: ["Reptilia", "Amphibia", "Aves", "Mammalia"],
    answer: "Mammalia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The adaptive importance of nuptial flight from termite colonies is to",
    options: [
      "disperse the reproductives in order to establish new colonies",
      "provide abundant food for birds and other animals during the early rains",
      "ensure cross-breeding between members of one colony and another",
      "expel the reproductives from the colony",
    ],
    answer: "disperse the reproductives in order to establish new colonies",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following can cause shrinkage of living cells?",
    options: [
      "Hypotonic solution",
      "Isotonic solution",
      "Deionized water",
      "Hypertonic solution",
    ],
    answer: "Hypertonic solution",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is true of leucocytes?",
    options: [
      "They are respiratory pigments",
      "They are most numerous and ramify all cells",
      "They are large and nucleated",
      "They are involved in blood clotting",
    ],
    answer: "They are large and nucleated",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The conversion of a nutrient into a molecule in the body of a consumer is referred to as",
    options: ["digestion", "assimilation", "absorption", "inhibition"],
    answer: "assimilation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The ability of a living organism to detect and respond to changes in the environment is referred to as",
    options: ["locomotion", "irritability", "growth", "taxis"],
    answer: "irritability",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In mammals, the exchange of nutrients and metabolic products occurs in the",
    options: ["lungs", "oesophagus", "trachea", "lymph"],
    answer: "lymph",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of an endospermous seed is",
    options: ["maize grain", "cashew nut", "cotton seed", "bean seed"],
    answer: "maize grain",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is true regarding the function of leucocytes?",
    options: [
      "They are respiratory pigments",
      "They are most numerous and ramify all cells",
      "They are large and nucleated",
      "They are involved in blood clotting",
    ],
    answer: "They are large and nucleated",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The movement response of a cockroach away from a light source can be described as",
    options: [
      "positive phototaxism",
      "negative phototaxism",
      "negative phototropism",
      "positive phototropism",
    ],
    answer: "negative phototaxism",
  },
  {
    question: "The vascular tissues in higher plants are responsible for",
    options: [
      "the movement of food and water",
      "suction pressure",
      "transpiration pull",
      "the transport of gases and water",
    ],
    answer: "the movement of food and water",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The sequence of the one-way gaseous exchange mechanism in a fish is",
    options: [
      "operculum → gills → mouth",
      "gills → operculum → mouth",
      "mouth → operculum → gills",
      "mouth → gills → operculum",
    ],
    answer: "mouth → gills → operculum",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The part of the mammalian ear responsible for the maintenance of balance is the",
    options: ["cochlea", "pinna", "perilymph", "ossicles"],
    answer: "cochlea",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The path followed by air as it passes through the lungs in mammals is",
    options: [
      "trachea → bronchi → bronchioles → alveoli",
      "bronchi → trachea → alveoli → bronchioles",
      "trachea → bronchioles → bronchi → alveoli",
      "bronchioles → alveoli → bronchi → trachea",
    ],
    answer: "trachea → bronchi → bronchioles → alveoli",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The interaction of a community of organisms with its abiotic environment constitutes",
    options: ["niche", "a food chain", "an ecosystem", "a microhabitat"],
    answer: "an ecosystem",
  },
  {
    question: "The vector of the malaria parasite is",
    options: [
      "female Aedes mosquito",
      "female Anopheles mosquito",
      "male Culex mosquito",
      "female Culex mosquito",
    ],
    answer: "female Anopheles mosquito",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used to measure relative humidity?",
    options: ["Hydrometer", "Thermometer", "Hygrometer", "Anemometer"],
    answer: "Hygrometer",
  },
  {
    question: "The wings of a bat and those of a bird are examples of",
    options: [
      "convergent evolution",
      "continuous variation",
      "coevolution",
      "divergent evolution",
    ],
    answer: "divergent evolution",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following pairs of diseases is caused by a virus?",
    options: [
      "Cholera and tuberculosis",
      "Measles and poliomyelitis",
      "Syphilis and gonorrhoea",
      "Whooping cough and leprosy",
    ],
    answer: "Measles and poliomyelitis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The smallest living organisms which share characteristics of both plants and animals are the",
    options: ["bacteria", "viruses", "protozoa", "fungi"],
    answer: "viruses",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Organisms that can be classified under the kingdom Protoctista include",
    options: [
      "bacteria and protozoa",
      "viruses and bacteria",
      "algae and protozoa",
      "algae and bacteria",
    ],
    answer: "algae and protozoa",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is most advanced in the evolutionary trend of animals?",
    options: ["Liver fluke", "Earthworm", "Snail", "Cockroach"],
    answer: "Cockroach",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is the lowest category of classification?",
    options: ["Class", "Species", "Family", "Genus"],
    answer: "Species",
  },
  {
    question: "Plants that show secondary growth are usually found among the",
    options: [
      "thallophytes",
      "pteridophytes",
      "monocotyledons",
      "dicotyledons",
    ],
    answer: "dicotyledons",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The fungi are distinct group of eukaryotes mainly because they have",
    options: [
      "spores",
      "no chlorophyll",
      "many fruiting bodies",
      "sexual and sexual reproduction",
    ],
    answer: "no chlorophyll",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An arthropod that is destructive at early stage of its life cycle is",
    options: ["butterfly", "mosquito", "bee", "millipede"],
    answer: "butterfly",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An animal body that can be cut along its axis in any plane to give two identical parts is said to be",
    options: [
      "radially symmetrical",
      "bilaterally symmetrical",
      "asymmetrical",
      "symmetrical",
    ],
    answer: "radially symmetrical",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following possesses mammary gland?",
    options: ["Dogfish", "Whale", "Shark", "Catfish"],
    answer: "Whale",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The feature that links birds to reptiles in evolution is the possession of",
    options: ["feathers", "break", "skeleton", "scales"],
    answer: "scales",
  },
  {
    question: "Countershading is an adaptive feature that enables animals to",
    options: [
      "fight enemies",
      "remain undetected",
      "warn enemies",
      "attract mates",
    ],
    answer: "remain undetected",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following plant structures lacks a waterproof cuticle?",
    options: ["leaf", "stem", "root", "shoot"],
    answer: "root",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the mammalian male reproductive system, the part that serves as a passage for both urine and semen is the",
    options: ["urethra", "ureter", "bladder", "seminal vesicle"],
    answer: "urethra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In plants which of the following is required in minute quantities for growth?",
    options: ["Copper", "Potassium", "Phosphorus", "Sodium"],
    answer: "Copper",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following organisms is both parasitic and autotrophic?",
    options: ["Sundew", "Loran thus", "Rhizopus", "Tapeworm"],
    answer: "Sundew",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A function of the hydrochloric acid produced in the human stomach during digestion is to",
    options: [
      "neutralize the effect of bile",
      "coagulate milk protein and emulsify fats",
      "stop the action of ptyalin",
      "break up food into smaller particles",
    ],
    answer: "stop the action of ptyalin",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a polysaccharide?",
    options: ["Glucose", "Sucrose", "Maltose", "Cellulose"],
    answer: "Cellulose",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The presence of stilt roots, pneumatophores, sunken stomata and salt glands are adaptive features of plants found in the",
    options: [
      "tropical rainforest",
      "mangrove swamps",
      "grassland",
      "montane forest",
    ],
    answer: "mangrove swamps",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Plants of temperate origin can be grown in tropical areas in the vegetation zones of the",
    options: [
      "rain forest",
      "Guinea savanna",
      "Sudan savanna",
      "montane forest",
    ],
    answer: "Guinea savanna",
  },
  {
    question: "The water cycle is maintained mainly by",
    options: [
      "evaporation of water in the environment",
      "evaporation and condensation of water in the environment",
      "condensation of water in the environment",
      "transpiration and respiration in plants",
    ],
    answer: "evaporation and condensation of water in the environment",
  },
  {
    question: "Organisms living in an estuarine habitat are adapted to",
    options: [
      "withstand wide fluctuations in temperature",
      "survive only in water with low salinity",
      "withstand wide fluctuations in salinity",
      "feed only on phytoplankton and dead organic matter",
    ],
    answer: "withstand wide fluctuations in salinity",
  },
  {
    question: "The basking of Agama lizards in the sun is to",
    options: [
      "change the color of their body",
      "raise their body temperature to become active",
      "fight to defend their territories",
      "attract the female for courtship",
    ],
    answer: "raise their body temperature to become active",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The significance of a very large number of termites involved in nuptial swarming is to",
    options: [
      "provide birds with plenty of food",
      "ensure their perpetuation despite predatory pressure",
      "search for a favorable place to breed",
      "ensure that every individual gets a mate",
    ],
    answer: "ensure their perpetuation despite predatory pressure",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The use and disuse of body parts and the inheritance of acquired traits were used to explain",
    options: [
      "Darwin's theory",
      "Lamarck's theory",
      "genetic drift",
      "gene flow",
    ],
    answer: "Lamarck's theory",
  },
  {
    question:
      "From his study of Galapagos finches, Darwin derived his theory of evolution from",
    options: [
      "comparative anatomy",
      "comparative physiology",
      "fossil remains",
      "comparative embryology",
    ],
    answer: "comparative anatomy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process in which complex substances are broken down into simpler ones is referred to as",
    options: ["anabolism", "catabolism", "metabolism", "tropism"],
    answer: "catabolism",
  },
  {
    question: "The organ which is sensitive to light in Euglena is the",
    options: ["gullet", "flagellum", "chloroplast", "eyespot"],
    answer: "eyespot",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The organelles present in cells that are actively respiring and photosynthesizing are",
    options: [
      "lysosomes and ribosomes",
      "Golgi apparatus and endoplasmic reticulum",
      "nucleus and centrioles",
      "mitochondria and chloroplast",
    ],
    answer: "mitochondria and chloroplast",
  },
  {
    question: "Taenia solium can be found in",
    options: ["cow", "goat", "dog", "pig"],
    answer: "pig",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following describes a characteristic of arthropods?",
    options: [
      "The organism finds it easy to grow freely",
      "the organism has a pair of jointed appendages",
      "the body is not divided into a number of segments",
      "the body is covered by chitin",
    ],
    answer: "the body is covered by chitin",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following distinguishes a butterfly from a moth?",
    options: [
      "the wings of butterfly rest horizontally but those of moth rest vertically",
      "Both are active during the day",
      "they have similar antennae",
      "the abdomen of moth is fatter than that of butterfly",
    ],
    answer:
      "the wings of butterfly rest horizontally but those of moth rest vertically",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following types of feathers is used for flight in birds?",
    options: ["Quill", "Filo plume", "Covert", "Down"],
    answer: "Quill",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The plants that grow in deserts or very dry areas are referred to as",
    options: ["mesophytes", "hydrophytes", "epiphytes", "xerophytes"],
    answer: "xerophytes",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is the simplest living organism?",
    options: ["Paramecium", "Virus", "Amoeba", "Chlamydomonas"],
    answer: "Amoeba",
  },
  {
    question: "Proboscis is a structure that is mostly found in",
    options: ["insects", "tapeworms", "amphibians", "molluscs"],
    answer: "insects",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The structural adaptation of desert plants for water conservation is",
    options: [
      "broad leaves with numerous stomata",
      "spongy mesophyll",
      "spiny leaves",
      "prominent stomata in leaves",
    ],
    answer: "spiny leaves",
  },
  {
    question: "The long and sharp clawed feet of birds is an adaptation for",
    options: [
      "crushing seeds",
      "scooping mud",
      "tearing flesh",
      "grasping prey",
    ],
    answer: "grasping prey",
  },
  {
    question:
      "During the manufacture of food by plants, which of the following organisms use energy from the sun?",
    options: [
      "anabaena",
      "sulphur bacteria",
      "Nitrosomonas sp.",
      "Nitrobacter sp.",
    ],
    answer: "anabaena",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Movement of minerals and chemical compounds within a plant occurs during",
    options: ["osmosis", "translocation", "transpiration", "diffusion"],
    answer: "translocation",
  },
  {
    question: "The enzyme that is present in the saliva is",
    options: ["rennin", "lipase", "pepsin", "ptyalin"],
    answer: "ptyalin",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Plants that have special devices for trapping and digesting insects are",
    options: ["carnivorous", "symbiotic", "parasitic", "saprophytic"],
    answer: "carnivorous",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process of transforming the chemical energy of cellular fuels into the high energy bonds of ATP in plants is",
    options: ["autotropism", "photosynthesis", "photolysis", "respiration"],
    answer: "respiration",
  },
  {
    question: "Fungi are referred to as heterotrophs because they",
    options: [
      "are filamentous",
      "lack chlorophyll",
      "have mycelium",
      "lack roots",
    ],
    answer: "lack chlorophyll",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of a parasitic protozoan is",
    options: ["Paramecium", "Plasmodium", "Euglena", "Chlamydomonas"],
    answer: "Plasmodium",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which blood cells are involved in the immune response of vertebrates?",
    options: ["Phagocytes", "lymphocytes", "erythrocytes", "monocytes"],
    answer: "lymphocytes",
  },
  {
    question: "The blood circulatory system of vertebrates consists of",
    options: [
      "heart, arteries, capillaries, and veins",
      "heart, aorta, capillaries, and veins",
      "heart, aorta, arteries, and veins",
      "heart, vena cava, arteries, and veins",
    ],
    answer: "heart, arteries, capillaries, and veins",
  },
  {
    question: "A plant tissue that carries water and mineral salts is the",
    options: ["cambium", "xylem", "cortex", "phloem"],
    answer: "xylem",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following helps in the clotting of blood?",
    options: ["Red blood cells", "White blood cells", "Plasma", "Platelets"],
    answer: "Platelets",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following forms about 55% of the volume of the blood in man?",
    options: ["leucocytes", "platelets", "plasma", "erythrocytes"],
    answer: "plasma",
  },
  {
    question: "The part of the mammalian skin involved in excretion is the",
    options: [
      "sweat glands",
      "Malpighian layer",
      "sebaceous gland",
      "horny layer",
    ],
    answer: "sweat glands",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a waste product of an insect?",
    options: ["Alkaloids", "Uric acid", "Sweat", "Mucilage"],
    answer: "Uric acid",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The main structure in vertebrates that supports and protects the body is the",
    options: ["skeleton", "ligament", "muscle", "joint"],
    answer: "skeleton",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The chitin in the exoskeleton of many arthropods is strengthened by",
    options: ["lipids", "proteins", "calcium compounds", "organic salt"],
    answer: "calcium compounds",
  },
  {
    question: "The transfer of pollen grains from the anther to a stigma is",
    options: ["propagation", "placentation", "pollination", "fertilization"],
    answer: "pollination",
  },
  {
    question: "The male reproductive organ of a flower is the",
    options: ["carpel", "stamen", "petal", "sepal"],
    answer: "stamen",
  },
  {
    question: "The gland that is found just below the hypothalamus is the",
    options: ["parathyroid", "adrenal", "pituitary", "thyroid"],
    answer: "pituitary",
  },
  {
    question: "The most important plant hormone is",
    options: ["cytokinin", "abscisic acid", "auxin", "gibberellin"],
    answer: "auxin",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The sensory cell that responds to dim light is referred to as the",
    options: ["cone", "lens", "rod", "iris"],
    answer: "rod",
  },
  {
    question: "The absence of anti-diuretic hormone in humans results in",
    options: [
      "decreasing dehydration",
      "drastic dehydration",
      "eliminating dehydration",
      "increasing dehydration",
    ],
    answer: "increasing dehydration",
  },
  {
    question: "Oestrogen is a hormone that is synthesized in the",
    options: ["ovaries", "testes", "anterior pituitary", "adrenal cortex"],
    answer: "ovaries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The eye defect caused by the development of cloudy areas in the lenses is",
    options: ["presbyopia", "cataract", "myopia", "hypermetropia"],
    answer: "cataract",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following are gametes?",
    options: ["Gonads", "Ova", "Zygotes", "Spermatocytes"],
    answer: "Ova",
  },
  {
    question: "In plants, the first formed food is usually",
    options: ["fat", "protein", "glucose", "starch"],
    answer: "glucose",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the forms in which carbohydrates are transported in plants is",
    options: ["sucrose", "maltose", "starch", "glucose"],
    answer: "sucrose",
  },
  {
    question: "The lowest level of organization in living organisms is",
    options: ["organ", "cell", "system", "tissue"],
    answer: "cell",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is the most complex according to their cellular level of organization?",
    options: ["Heart", "Hair", "Euglena", "Hydra"],
    answer: "Hair",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following organisms is multi-cellular?",
    options: ["Chlamydomonas", "Spirogyra", "Amoeba", "Euglena"],
    answer: "Spirogyra",
  },
  {
    question: "In bryophytes, sex organs are produced in the",
    options: ["protonema", "sporophyte", "gametophyte", "rhizoid"],
    answer: "gametophyte",
  },
  {
    question: "Seed plants are the most dominant vegetation on land because of",
    options: [
      "their motile gametes",
      "their ability to photosynthesize",
      "efficient seed dispersal",
      "availability of water",
    ],
    answer: "efficient seed dispersal",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is an arboreal organism?",
    options: ["Elephant", "Fish", "Antelope", "Bird"],
    answer: "Bird",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A circulatory system is very essential in mammals but not in smaller organisms like Amoeba because",
    options: [
      "amoeba lives in freshwater",
      "diffusion is sufficient to transport materials in Amoeba",
      "amoeba lacks blood containing haemoglobin",
      "amoeba exhibits anaerobic respiration",
    ],
    answer: "diffusion is sufficient to transport materials in Amoeba",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In vascular plants, the sieve tubes and companion cells are present in the",
    options: ["cambium", "cortex", "xylem", "phloem"],
    answer: "phloem",
  },
  {
    question: "The stomata of leaves are similar in function to the",
    options: [
      "pharynx of humans",
      "scales of fish",
      "spiracle of insects",
      "trachea of toads",
    ],
    answer: "spiracle of insects",
  },
  {
    question: "The use of moist skin for respiration in amphibians is known as",
    options: [
      "cellular respiration",
      "cutaneous respiration",
      "buccal respiration",
      "pulmonary respiration",
    ],
    answer: "cutaneous respiration",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Water in plants is removed as water vapour through the process of",
    options: ["diffusion", "osmosis", "evaporation", "transpiration"],
    answer: "transpiration",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of an organ of perennation in plants is",
    options: ["rhizome", "seed", "petal of a flower", "calyx of flower"],
    answer: "seed",
  },
  {
    question: "Alternation of generation is a feature shown in",
    options: ["mosses", "fungi", "grasses", "conifers"],
    answer: "mosses",
  },
  {
    question:
      "I. Growth is mainly apical II. Growth is specific with definite shape III. Growth is throughout life. Which of the above correctly describes the growth pattern in plants?",
    options: [
      "I, II and III only",
      "II and III only",
      "I and II only",
      "I and III only",
    ],
    answer: "I and III only",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Coordination and regulation of body activities in mammals are achieved by the",
    options: [
      "nerves and muscle",
      "nerves and hormones",
      "nerves only",
      "hormones only",
    ],
    answer: "nerves and hormones",
  },
  {
    question: "The Cerebellum of the Brain controls",
    options: [
      "reflex action",
      "muscular activity",
      "emotional expressions",
      "the Endocrine system",
    ],
    answer: "muscular activity",
  },
  {
    question: "The part of the brain responsible for peristalsis is the",
    options: [
      "Olfactory Lobe",
      "Medulla Oblongata",
      "Hypothalamus",
      "Thalamus",
    ],
    answer: "Medulla Oblongata",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used for measuring atmospheric pressure?",
    options: ["Hydrometer", "Hygrometer", "Thermometer", "Barometer"],
    answer: "Barometer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The influence of soil on organisms in a habitat is referred to as",
    options: ["edaphic", "physiographic", "biotic", "topographic"],
    answer: "edaphic",
  },
  {
    question: "The genetic make-up of an organism is described as",
    options: ["allele", "chromosome", "phenotype", "genotype"],
    answer: "genotype",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The major limiting factor of productivity in the aquatic habitat is",
    options: ["food", "temperature", "water", "sunlight"],
    answer: "food",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following group of organisms feeds directly on green plants?",
    options: [
      "Primary Consumers",
      "Secondary Consumers",
      "Producers",
      "Decomposers",
    ],
    answer: "Primary Consumers",
  },
  {
    question: "A characteristic feature of tropical rainforest is that it",
    options: [
      "Contains trees with narrow leaves",
      "Contains large number of plant species",
      "Contains fewer number of plant species",
      "Has total annual rainfall of less than 50cm",
    ],
    answer: "Contains large number of plant species",
  },
  {
    question: "The study of how and why population size changes over time is",
    options: [
      "Population estimation",
      "Population dynamics",
      "Population ecology",
      "Population Cycle",
    ],
    answer: "Population dynamics",
  },
  {
    question: "A severe and long dry season is a characteristic feature of",
    options: [
      "Sahel Savanna",
      "Mangrove Swamps",
      "Sudan Savanna",
      "Guinea Savanna",
    ],
    answer: "Sahel Savanna",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a nitrogen fixing blue-green algae of soil?",
    options: ["Rhizobium", "Nitrosomonas", "Clostridium", "Anabaena"],
    answer: "Anabaena",
  },
  {
    question: "The soil with highest water retaining capacity is",
    options: ["Clayey Soil", "Stoney soil", "Sandy soil", "Loamy Soil"],
    answer: "Clayey Soil",
  },
  {
    question: "The causative agent of Poliomyelitis is",
    options: ["Virus", "Fungus", "Protozoan", "Bacterium"],
    answer: "Virus",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the ways of controlling noise pollution in urban areas is",
    options: [
      "by siting industries away from residential areas",
      "that fuel should be completely combusted by engines",
      "by planting trees on both sides of the road",
      "by wearing ear devices",
    ],
    answer: "by siting industries away from residential areas",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A constituent of the exhaust fumes from electricity generating sets which causes serious pollution is",
    options: [
      "Carbon (II) Oxide",
      "Water Vapour",
      "Ozone",
      "Carbon (IV) Oxide",
    ],
    answer: "Carbon (II) Oxide",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is true of small pox?",
    options: [
      "It is transmitted by bacteria",
      "It can effectively be controlled with antibiotics",
      "It can effectively be controlled by vaccination",
      "It is a water-borne infection",
    ],
    answer: "It can effectively be controlled by vaccination",
  },
  {
    question: "A pollutant that is mostly associated with acid rain is",
    options: ["Nitrogen (IV) Oxide", "Ozone", "Fluorine"],
    answer: "Nitrogen (IV) Oxide",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When the adults have reached a certain degree of weakness, the process of binary fission is replaced by conjugation in",
    options: ["Paramecium", "Euglena", "Amoeba", "Plasmodium"],
    answer: "Paramecium",
  },
  {
    question: "Whorls, arches, loops and compounds are types of variation in",
    options: ["Colour", "Finger prints", "Hair Colour", "Blood group"],
    answer: "Finger prints",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A couple has 10 children, all female. Which of the following best explains the situation?",
    options: [
      "The sex determination was by the man's X chromosome",
      "The man's sperm count is low",
      "The woman is not capable of producing male children",
      "The sex determination was by the man's Y chromosome",
    ],
    answer: "The sex determination was by the man's X chromosome",
  },
  {
    question: "The mineral element needed for the formation of thyroxine is",
    options: ["Calcium", "Potassium", "Phosphorus", "Iodine"],
    answer: "Iodine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One adaptation shown by hydrophytes in freshwater habitats is the",
    options: [
      "waxy cuticle on shoot surface",
      "poor development of roots and xylem tissues",
      "well-developed roots and supporting system",
      "leaves reduced to spines",
    ],
    answer: "poor development of roots and xylem tissues",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following uses diffusion as the principal method of gaseous exchange?",
    options: ["grasshopper", "rat", "lizard", "earthworm"],
    answer: "earthworm",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The theory that supports the view that the large muscles developed by an athlete will be passed on to the offspring was proposed by",
    options: ["Mendel", "Darwin", "Lamark", "Pasteur"],
    answer: "Lamark",
  },
  {
    question: "The chromosomes of members of the kingdom Monera are within the",
    options: ["nucleoplasm", "nucleus", "nucleolus", "cytoplasm"],
    answer: "cytoplasm",
  },
  {
    question: "The mangrove swamp in Nigeria is restricted to the",
    options: [
      "Sahel savanna",
      "Guinea savanna",
      "Tropical rainforest",
      "Sudan savanna",
    ],
    answer: "Tropical rainforest",
  },
  {
    question: "The pancreas secretes enzymes for the digestion of",
    options: [
      "fats, proteins, and carbohydrates",
      "fats, vitamins, and cellulose",
      "fats, carbohydrates, and vitamins",
      "proteins, cellulose, and minerals",
    ],
    answer: "fats, proteins, and carbohydrates",
  },
  {
    question: "The causative agent of bird flu is a",
    options: ["protozoan", "virus", "bacterium", "fungus"],
    answer: "virus",
  },
  {
    question: "A water medium is necessary for fertilization in",
    options: ["conifers", "angiosperms", "ferns", "fungi"],
    answer: "ferns",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of a sex-linked trait is the",
    options: [
      "colour of the skin in humans",
      "ability to roll the tongue",
      "possession of facial hair in adult humans",
      "ability to grow long hair in females",
    ],
    answer: "possession of facial hair in adult humans",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which of the following Nigerian states can montane vegetation be found?",
    options: ["Bauchi", "Plateau", "Taraba", "Enugu"],
    answer: "Plateau",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is true of cloning?",
    options: [
      "It is welcomed as an ethically and normally sound science",
      "It involves the asexual multiplication of the tissues of the original organism",
      "The clone is similar to but not exactly like the original organism",
      "Only one cell of the original organism is needed to initiate the process",
    ],
    answer:
      "The clone is similar to but not exactly like the original organism",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process of shedding the exoskeleton of an arthropod is known as",
    options: ["ecdysis", "in star formation", "metamorphosis", "osmosis"],
    answer: "ecdysis",
  },
  {
    question: "A major cause of constipation in humans is",
    options: [
      "lack of roughage",
      "vitamin B deficiency",
      "vitamin E deficiency",
      "lack of salts",
    ],
    answer: "lack of roughage",
  },
  {
    question: "In mammals, the organ directly on top of the kidney is the",
    options: ["adrenal gland", "prostate gland", "pancreas", "thyroid gland"],
    answer: "adrenal gland",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An accurate identification of a rapist can be carried out by conducting a",
    options: [
      "RNA analysis",
      "blood group test",
      "behavioral traits test",
      "DNA analysis",
    ],
    answer: "DNA analysis",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of a fish that aestivates is",
    options: ["croaker", "lung fish", "shark", "catfish"],
    answer: "lung fish",
  },
  {
    question: "The opening and closing of the stoma are regulated by",
    options: ["respiration", "osmosis", "diffusion", "transpiration"],
    answer: "osmosis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is common to the mosquito, housefly, and blackfly?",
    options: [
      "They are parasites of man",
      "Their immature stages are aquatic",
      "They undergo complete metamorphosis",
      "Their adults have two pairs of wings",
    ],
    answer: "They undergo complete metamorphosis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The organs that will be most useful to giant African rats in finding their way in underground habitats are the",
    options: ["nostrils", "eyes", "vibrissae", "tails"],
    answer: "vibrissae",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A crucible of 5g weighed 10g after filling with fresh soil. It is then heated in an oven at 100°C for 1 hour. After cooling in a desiccator, the weight was 8g. The percentage of water in the soil is",
    options: ["0.8", "0.2", "0.4", "0.6"],
    answer: "0.4",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The waste product of plants used in the conversion of hide to leather is",
    options: ["alkaloid", "resin", "tannin", "gum"],
    answer: "tannin",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The correct sequence of the movement of urea during formation is",
    options: [
      "glomerulus - Bowman's capsule - convoluted tubule - Henle's loop - collecting tubule",
      "convoluted tubule - glomerulus - Henle's loop - Bowman's capsule - collecting tubule",
      "glomerulus - Bowman's capsule - convoluted tubule - Henle's loop - collecting tubule",
      "convoluted tubule - Bowman's capsule - Henle's loop - glomerulus - collecting tubule",
    ],
    answer:
      "glomerulus - Bowman's capsule - convoluted tubule - Henle's loop - collecting tubule",
  },
  {
    question: "In lizards, the lowering of the gular fold is used to",
    options: [
      "defend their territory",
      "attract mates",
      "frighten enemies",
      "catch insects",
    ],
    answer: "frighten enemies",
  },
  {
    question: "The photosynthetic pigments include",
    options: [
      "chloroplast and cytochromes",
      "melanin and haemoglobin",
      "chlorophyll and carotenoids",
      "carotenoids and haemoglobin",
    ],
    answer: "chlorophyll and carotenoids",
  },
  {
    question: "The highest level of ecological organization is the",
    options: ["ecosystem", "niche", "biosphere", "population"],
    answer: "biosphere",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A biotic factor which affects the distribution and abundance of organisms in a terrestrial habitat is",
    options: ["pH", "competition", "temperature", "light"],
    answer: "temperature",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The eye defect that arises because the cornea is not curved smoothly is",
    options: [
      "astigmatism",
      "short-sightedness",
      "long-sightedness",
      "presbyopia",
    ],
    answer: "astigmatism",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is an example of parasitism?",
    options: [
      "a squirrel living in an abandoned nest of a bird",
      "mistletoe growing on an orange tree",
      "fungi growing on a dead tree branch",
      "cattle egrets taking tasks from the body of cattle",
    ],
    answer: "mistletoe growing on an orange tree",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The increasing order of particle size in the following soil types is",
    options: [
      "sand - clay - gravel",
      "clay - silt - sand - gravel",
      "silt - clay - sand - gravel",
      "clay - sand - silt - gravel",
    ],
    answer: "clay - silt - sand - gravel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following factors can bring about competition in a population?",
    options: ["emigration", "drought", "mortality", "dispersion"],
    answer: "drought",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Stunted growth and poor root development are a result of a deficiency in",
    options: ["phosphorus", "calcium", "sulphur", "iron"],
    answer: "phosphorus",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following structures is a protective adaptive feature of the Agama Lizard to the environment?",
    options: ["Nuchal crest", "Claws", "Scaly skin", "Gular fold"],
    answer: "Scaly skin",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following adapts an insect for feeding?",
    options: [
      "suitable mouthparts",
      "paired antennae",
      "segmented body",
      "jointed appendages",
    ],
    answer: "suitable mouthparts",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following results from the cross between Yy and Yy?",
    options: ["2Yy-2yy", "2Yy:yy:YY", "YY:2Yy:yy", "YY: Yy:2yy"],
    answer: "YY:2Yy:yy",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT part of the carbon cycle?",
    options: [
      "Organic carbon",
      "Decomposition",
      "Nitrates formation",
      "Photosynthesis",
    ],
    answer: "Nitrates formation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "I. Tissues II. System III. Cell IV. Organs Which of the above is the level of organization of a leaf?",
    options: ["IV", "I", "III", "II"],
    answer: "IV",
  },
  {
    question: "In cellular respiration, energy is stored in the form of",
    options: [
      "heat energy",
      "adenosine diphosphate",
      "adenosine monophosphate",
      "adenosine triphosphate",
    ],
    answer: "adenosine triphosphate",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The principal organ for the manufacture of food in autotrophy is the",
    options: ["root hair", "growing root", "mature fruit", "green leaf"],
    answer: "green leaf",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A disease that results from lack of iodine in the diet of humans is",
    options: ["beriberi", "scurvy", "rickets", "goiter"],
    answer: "goiter",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process whereby some organisms with certain favourable features get established in an area is",
    options: [
      "gene mutation",
      "dispersal",
      "overcrowding",
      "natural selection",
    ],
    answer: "natural selection",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The rise and fall of ocean water during the day is referred to as",
    options: ["gravity", "a pull", "tide", "zone"],
    answer: "tide",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a producer in an aquatic habitat?",
    options: ["Nymphaea", "Dryopteris", "planarian", "Similium"],
    answer: "Nymphaea",
  },
  {
    question: "The relationship that exists between a shark and Remora is",
    options: ["parasitism", "commensalism", "saprophytism", "symbiosis"],
    answer: "commensalism",
  },
  {
    question:
      "I. Tissue II. System III. Cell IV. Organ The correct sequence of increasing level of complexity is",
    options: ["IV-II-III", "I-II-III-IV", "IV-III-I-II", "III-I-IV-II"],
    answer: "III-I-IV-II",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is not an inheritable disease?",
    options: [
      "Poliomyelitis",
      "Sickle-cell anaemia",
      "Mental illness",
      "Haemophilia",
    ],
    answer: "Poliomyelitis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the fingerprint types occur most frequently in the population of human beings?",
    options: ["Double-loop", "Whorl", "Arch", "Loop"],
    answer: "Loop",
  },
  {
    question: "Beriberi results from a deficiency of",
    options: ["vitamin A", "vitamin E", "vitamin B", "vitamin C"],
    answer: "vitamin B",
  },
  {
    question: "Bacteria which add atmospheric nitrogen to the soil are",
    options: [
      "putrefying bacteria",
      "nitrifying bacteria",
      "nitrogen fixing bacteria",
      "denitrifying bacteria",
    ],
    answer: "nitrogen fixing bacteria",
  },
  {
    question: "The spines of the hedgehog is an adaptive feature for",
    options: ["Courtship", "defence", "water conservation", "obtaining food"],
    answer: "defence",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used to measure temperature?",
    options: ["Thermometer", "Hygrometer", "Anemometer", "Hydrometer"],
    answer: "Thermometer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In humans, puffiness and water retention in the body is a possible symptom of",
    options: [
      "bladder malfunction",
      "poor digestion",
      "kidney malfunction",
      "obesity",
    ],
    answer: "kidney malfunction",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The theory of evolution which postulates that all living organisms have a common ancestor was proposed by",
    options: ["Linnaeus", "Darwin", "Lamarck", "Mendel"],
    answer: "Darwin",
  },
  {
    question: "Mammals require roughage in their food to",
    options: [
      "provide energy",
      "slow down aging",
      "ease digestion",
      "prevent disease",
    ],
    answer: "ease digestion",
  },
  {
    question: "Variation can occur among offspring of living organisms because",
    options: [
      "seeds are produced by self-pollination",
      "zygotes are produced by cross-fertilisation",
      "they are produced by binary fission",
      "they are produced without fertilisation",
    ],
    answer: "zygotes are produced by cross-fertilisation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The most important biotic factors which affect plants and animals in the habitat are",
    options: [
      "temperature and rainfall",
      "temperature and turbidity",
      "salinity and relative humidity",
      "rainfall and relative humidity",
    ],
    answer: "temperature and rainfall",
  },
  {
    question: "The lowest unit of classification is the",
    options: ["Kingdom", "class", "phylum", "species"],
    answer: "species",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Two important processes involved in the absorption and transport of materials in plants are",
    options: [
      "flaccidity and turgidity",
      "diffusion and plasmolysis",
      "plasmolysis and capillarity",
      "osmosis and diffusion",
    ],
    answer: "osmosis and diffusion",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A series of organisms existing in an ecosystem through which energy is transformed can be referred to as",
    options: ["food cycle", "food chain", "pyramid of numbers", "food web"],
    answer: "food chain",
  },
  {
    question: "The cell organelle solely responsible for respiration is the",
    options: ["nucleus", "nucleolus", "endoplasmic reticulum", "mitochondrion"],
    answer: "mitochondrion",
  },
  {
    question: "In which part of Nigeria are Mangrove swamps found?",
    options: ["Chad Basin", "Niger Delta", "Benue Valley", "Mambilla Plateau"],
    answer: "Niger Delta",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The breeding methods that are useful in the selective breeding of animals and plants are",
    options: [
      "inbreeding and cross-breeding",
      "inbreeding and hetero-breeding",
      "inbreeding and out-breeding",
      "inbreeding and self-breeding",
    ],
    answer: "inbreeding and cross-breeding",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In a small unicellular organism, diffusion is sufficient for transport because",
    options: [
      "the surface area to volume ratio is small",
      "they have lungs for diffusion",
      "materials have to move over long distances",
      "the surface area to volume ratio is large",
    ],
    answer: "the surface area to volume ratio is large",
  },
  {
    question: "The number of chromosomes in a normal human cell is",
    options: ["23", "46", "48", "44"],
    answer: "46",
  },
  {
    question: "The variety of organisms found in a given habitat is known as",
    options: [
      "species richness",
      "biomass",
      "biodiversity",
      "population density",
    ],
    answer: "biodiversity",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The organism that absorbs nutrients from a decaying organic matter is a",
    options: ["producer", "decomposer", "herbivore", "carnivore"],
    answer: "decomposer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following represents the primary function of the ribosome in the cell?",
    options: [
      "Synthesis of DNA",
      "Synthesis of proteins",
      "Synthesis of RNA",
      "Replication of cells",
    ],
    answer: "Synthesis of proteins",
  },
  {
    question: "The failure of the heart to pump blood adequately can result in",
    options: ["anemia", "hypertension", "heart attack", "hypotension"],
    answer: "heart attack",
  },
  {
    question: "The physical appearance of an organism is referred to as its",
    options: ["genotype", "phenotype", "allele", "chromosome"],
    answer: "phenotype",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following organisms is a herbivore?",
    options: ["Lion", "Eagle", "Rabbit", "Shark"],
    answer: "Rabbit",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which process is responsible for the production of glucose in plants?",
    options: ["Respiration", "Fermentation", "Photosynthesis", "Transpiration"],
    answer: "Photosynthesis",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a characteristic of living organisms?",
    options: [
      "Ability to grow",
      "Ability to breathe",
      "Ability to move",
      "Ability to reproduce",
    ],
    answer: "Ability to reproduce",
  },
  {
    question: "An ecosystem consists of all the following EXCEPT",
    options: [
      "abiotic factors",
      "biotic factors",
      "human population",
      "atmospheric pressure",
    ],
    answer: "human population",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the primary function of chlorophyll in plants?",
    options: [
      "Absorbing light energy",
      "Absorbing nutrients",
      "Absorbing water",
      "Absorbing carbon dioxide",
    ],
    answer: "Absorbing light energy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following nutrients is most essential for growth and repair of tissues?",
    options: ["Carbohydrates", "Fats", "Proteins", "Vitamins"],
    answer: "Proteins",
  },
  {
    question: "The piercing and sucking mouth parts are found in",
    options: ["grasshoppers", "mosquitoes", "termites", "cockroaches"],
    answer: "mosquitoes",
  },
  {
    question: "The hormones that regulate plant growth are",
    options: [
      "ethylene and auxins",
      "auxin and gibberellins",
      "cytokinin and abscisic acid",
      "ethylene and gibberellins",
    ],
    answer: "auxin and gibberellins",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following pair of organisms exhibit parasitic association?",
    options: [
      "insect and plant",
      "cattle and egret",
      "shark and remora",
      "tsetse-fly and cattle",
    ],
    answer: "tsetse-fly and cattle",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following group of animals can withstand the rigour of the arid land?",
    options: [
      "locust, camel, lizard and snakes",
      "monkeys, chameleon, earthworm and grasshopper",
      "monkeys, grasshopper, snail and snakes",
      "lungfish, duck, butterfly and lizards",
    ],
    answer: "locust, camel, lizard and snakes",
  },
  {
    question: "Suture joint is found in the",
    options: ["hip", "ankle", "skull", "elbow"],
    answer: "skull",
  },
  {
    question: "The organelle responsible for osmoregulation in Paramecium is",
    options: [
      "flame cell",
      "nephridia",
      "contractile vacuole",
      "Malpighian tubule",
    ],
    answer: "contractile vacuole",
  },
  {
    question: "The platelets in mammalian blood are responsible for",
    options: [
      "transporting oxygen",
      "initiating clotting",
      "removing carbon (IV) oxide",
      "destroying micro-organisms",
    ],
    answer: "initiating clotting",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The most important factor that determines the different types of vegetation is",
    options: ["light", "wind", "temperature", "rainfall"],
    answer: "rainfall",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When testing for the presence of starch in a leaf, the reason for dipping the decolourised leaf in hot water is to",
    options: [
      "detect the starch",
      "kill the leaf",
      "soften the leaf",
      "remove the chlorophyll",
    ],
    answer: "soften the leaf",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The relationship between remora and shark can best be described as",
    options: ["parasitism", "amensalism", "mutualism", "commensalism"],
    answer: "commensalism",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The major characteristic of a fresh water habitat is the possession of",
    options: ["high turbidity", "high density", "low salinity", "high current"],
    answer: "low salinity",
  },
  {
    question: "The causative organism of cholera is",
    options: ["Clostridium sp", "shigella sp", "vibrio sp", "salmonella typhi"],
    answer: "vibrio sp",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process that takes place in the dark stage of photosynthesis is",
    options: [
      "oxidation of water",
      "photolysis of water",
      "oxidation of carbon (IV) oxide",
      "reduction of carbon (IV) oxide",
    ],
    answer: "reduction of carbon (IV) oxide",
  },
  {
    question: "Chlorofluorocarbons are air pollutants that originate from",
    options: [
      "crude oil refining",
      "coal mining",
      "motor vehicle exhaust",
      "cooling system",
    ],
    answer: "cooling system",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is organ level of organisation?",
    options: [
      "Volvox sp",
      "paramecium caudatum",
      "hydra viridis",
      "onion bulb",
    ],
    answer: "onion bulb",
  },
  {
    question: "The simplest form of reproduction is",
    options: ["conjugation", "budding", "spore formation", "binary fission"],
    answer: "binary fission",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a characteristic of wind-pollinated flower?",
    options: [
      "flowers lack nectar",
      "flowers are conspicuous",
      "flowers have perianths",
      "flowers are bisexual",
    ],
    answer: "flowers lack nectar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process required for formation of gamete in sexual reproduction is",
    options: ["implantation", "fertilisation", "mitosis", "meiosis"],
    answer: "meiosis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In an experiment to determine the humus in a soil sample the following results were obtained: Mass of dish - 20g, Mass of dry soil - 7.5g, Mass of dish + soil after burning = 25g. The percentage of humus in the given sample is",
    options: ["9.1", "37.5", "12.5", "33.3"],
    answer: "37.5",
  },
  {
    question: "The presence of termites and earthworms in soil promote",
    options: [
      "porosity and fertility",
      "porosity and aeration",
      "aeration and fertility",
      "acidity and aeration",
    ],
    answer: "porosity and fertility",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In a 15m² habitat, the total number of Tridax counted using a 1.6m² quadrant thrown randomly 50 times was 400. What is the Tridax?",
    options: ["12", "16", "8", "5"],
    answer: "16",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a sex-link character?",
    options: ["Dwarfism", "Albinism", "Tongue rolling", "Colour blindness"],
    answer: "Colour blindness",
  },
  {
    question: "The outer-most tissue of the herbaceous roots is the",
    options: ["cuticle", "pericycle", "epidermis", "endodermis"],
    answer: "epidermis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The respective tissues that transport water and manufactured food in plants are",
    options: [
      "xylem and phloem",
      "phloem and tracheid",
      "phloem and xylem",
      "xylem and tracheid",
    ],
    answer: "xylem and phloem",
  },
  {
    question: "An adaptive feature of plants in the savanna is",
    options: ["fissured bark", "few grasses", "tall trees", "long lifespan"],
    answer: "fissured bark",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A grasshopper's cuticle becomes green during the season and black after fire. The reason for the change is ---",
    options: ["obtain food", "predators", "secure mates", "escape detection"],
    answer: "escape detection",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is the most advanced plant?",
    options: ["merchantia", "Dryopteris", "Chlamydomonas", "Spirogyra"],
    answer: "Dryopteris",
  },
  {
    question: "The soil type with the least ability to retain nutrients is",
    options: ["sandy loam", "clay loam", "loam", "sand"],
    answer: "sand",
  },
  {
    question: "A hummingbird is able to feed on nectar because its beak is",
    options: [
      "short, slender and ridged",
      "short, strong and conical",
      "long, slender and slightly curved",
      "long, wide and slightly curved",
    ],
    answer: "long, slender and slightly curved",
  },
  {
    question: "The effect of overcrowding is",
    options: [
      "immigration",
      "reduced competition",
      "emigration",
      "decrease in population size",
    ],
    answer: "emigration",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The major factor that determines the distribution of organisms in the aquatic habitat is",
    options: ["light", "temperature", "salinity", "turbidity"],
    answer: "salinity",
  },
  {
    question: "The main function of the placenta is",
    options: [
      "gas exchange",
      "nutrient exchange",
      "waste elimination",
      "all of the above",
    ],
    answer: "all of the above",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following represents a limiting factor for the distribution of organisms in a habitat?",
    options: ["hunting", "light", "poaching", "harvesting"],
    answer: "light",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The adaptations in mangrove swamp plants that help them to survive in salty conditions include the presence of",
    options: [
      "aerial roots",
      "pneumatophores",
      "floating leaves",
      "deep roots",
    ],
    answer: "pneumatophores",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The condition necessary for the preparation of a permanent slide is",
    options: ["mounting", "staining", "fixation", "slicing"],
    answer: "fixation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The correct order of processes involved in the evolution of bacteria is",
    options: [
      "Mutation, selection, variation",
      "Variation, selection, mutation",
      "Selection, mutation, variation",
      "Mutation, variation, selection",
    ],
    answer: "Mutation, variation, selection",
  },

  {
    question:
      "A beaker of pond water containing few specimens of Euglena was placed in a dark room for two weeks. At the end of this period, the specimens of Euglena were still alive because they were",
    options: [
      "able to carry out holozoic nutrition",
      "able to carry out photosynthesis using carbon dioxide in the pond water",
      "better adapted to life in darkness than to life in light",
      "not overcrowded",
    ],
    answer:
      "able to carry out photosynthesis using carbon dioxide in the pond water",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The cytoplasm of the cell is considered a very important component because it",
    options: [
      "regulates the amount of energy in the cell",
      "suspends all cell organelles",
      "is the outermost part of the cell",
      "is solely responsible for cell division",
    ],
    answer: "suspends all cell organelles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Red blood cells were found to have burst open after being placed in distil for an hour. This phenomenon is known as",
    options: ["plasmolysis", "diffusion", "haemolysis", "wilting"],
    answer: "haemolysis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The curvature movement of plants in response to the stimulus of water is called",
    options: ["hydrotropism", "geotropism", "phototropism", "thigmotropism"],
    answer: "hydrotropism",
  },
  {
    question: "The overall reaction in glycolysis can be summarised as",
    options: [
      "C6H12O5 --C3H4O3 + 4H + ATP",
      "C6H12O6 ---- 2CH4O3 + 4H + 2ATP",
      "C6H12O6---> 2CH4O3 + 4H + ADP",
      "C6H12O6 2C3H4O3+ 4H + 2ADP",
    ],
    answer: "C6H12O6 ---- 2CH4O3 + 4H + 2ATP",
  },
  {
    question: "The longest bone in the body is the",
    options: ["humerous", "femur", "scapula", "tibia"],
    answer: "femur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following structures is not a skeletal material?",
    options: ["Chitin", "Cartilage", "Bone", "Muscle"],
    answer: "Muscle",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The reason why the flow of blood through the capillaries is very slow is",
    options: [
      "because the walls of capillaries are very thin",
      "to avoid high blood pressure",
      "to ensure that the individual does not get dizzy",
      "to allow adequate time for exchange of materials",
    ],
    answer: "to allow adequate time for exchange of materials",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following groups of organisms has kidney as their excretory organ?",
    options: [
      "Fishes, amphibians, birds, man",
      "Fishes, amphibians, annelids, insects",
      "Fishes, reptiles, birds, tapeworms",
      "Fishes protozoans, amphibians, man",
    ],
    answer: "Fishes, amphibians, birds, man",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following features is not a characteristic of arteries?",
    options: [
      "possess values at internals throughout their length",
      "have thick muscular and elastic walls",
      "carry blood away from the heart",
      "transport oxygenated blood with the exception of the pulmonary artery",
    ],
    answer: "possess values at internals throughout their length",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What physiological term can be used to describe the regulation of the body temperature of the lizard?",
    options: ["Homeostasis", "Homeothermy", "Poikilothermy", "Osmoregulation"],
    answer: "Poikilothermy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The reason why hospitals use saline solutions as drip instead of water is",
    options: [
      "because salt is a preservative",
      "to prevent contamination of the body",
      "to maintain the composition of body fluids",
      "to increase the number of blood cells",
    ],
    answer: "to maintain the composition of body fluids",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The part of the ear which contains nerve cells sensitive to sound vibrations is the",
    options: ["cochlea", "ampulla", "tympanum", "malleus"],
    answer: "cochlea",
  },
  {
    question: "Spectacles with convex lenses correct long-sightedness by",
    options: [
      "converging the light rays before they enter the eye",
      "diverging the light rays before they enter the eye",
      "reducing light intensity before it enters the eye",
      "increasing light intensity before it enters the eye",
    ],
    answer: "converging the light rays before they enter the eye",
  },
  {
    question: "A seed of a flowering plant can best be described as",
    options: [
      "radicle and plumule",
      "the developed ovule",
      "the embryo and endosperm",
      "developed ovary",
    ],
    answer: "the embryo and endosperm",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following processes removes carbon from the atmosphere?",
    options: [
      "Putrefaction",
      "Photosynthesis",
      "volcanic eruption",
      "Burning fuels",
    ],
    answer: "Photosynthesis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following cycles involves the process of precipitation and transpiration?",
    options: ["Water cycles", "Carbon cycle", "Nitrogen cycle", "oxygen cycle"],
    answer: "Water cycles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the critical limiting factor for plants below the photic zone in an aquatic ecosystem?",
    options: [
      "Availability of nutrients",
      "Availability of water",
      "intensity of light",
      "Carbon dioxide concentration",
    ],
    answer: "intensity of light",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used to estimate the number of plants in a habitat?",
    options: ["Pooter", "Pitfall trap", "Quadrat", "Sweep net"],
    answer: "Quadrat",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following statements is true about sandy soil?",
    options: [
      "has limited air space",
      "is light and easy to dig",
      "drains slowly",
      "is heavy and poorly aerated",
    ],
    answer: "is light and easy to dig",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following organisms is a primary consumer?",
    options: ["Dog", "Sheep", "Grass", "Fungus"],
    answer: "Sheep",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following statements best describes the organism designated R?",
    options: [
      "feeds on S.",
      "is a primary consumer.",
      "is a producer as well as a consumer",
      "is a secondary consumer",
    ],
    answer: "is a primary consumer.",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following diseases is not hereditary?",
    options: ["Albinism", "Scabies", "Haemophilia", "Colour blindness"],
    answer: "Scabies",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A beaker of pond water containing few specimens of Euglena was placed in a dark room for two weeks. At the end of this period, the specimens of Euglena were still alive because they were",
    options: [
      "able to carry out holozoic nutrition",
      "able to carry out photosynthesis using carbon dioxide in the pond water",
      "better adapted to life in darkness than to life in light",
      "not overcrowded",
    ],
    answer:
      "able to carry out photosynthesis using carbon dioxide in the pond water",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The cytoplasm of the cell is considered a very important component because it",
    options: [
      "regulates the amount of energy in the cell",
      "suspends all cell organelles",
      "is the outermost part of the cell",
      "is solely responsible for cell division",
    ],
    answer: "suspends all cell organelles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Red blood cells were found to have burst open after being placed in distil for an hour. This phenomenon is known as",
    options: ["plasmolysis", "diffusion", "haemolysis", "wilting"],
    answer: "haemolysis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The curvature movement of plants in response to the stimulus of water is called",
    options: ["hydrotropism", "geotropism", "phototropism", "thigmotropism"],
    answer: "hydrotropism",
  },
  {
    question: "The overall reaction in glycolysis can be summarised as",
    options: [
      "C6H12O5 --C3H4O3 + 4H + ATP",
      "C6H12O6 ---- 2CH4O3 + 4H + 2ATP",
      "C6H12O6---> 2CH4O3 + 4H + ADP",
      "C6H12O6 2C3H4O3+ 4H + 2ADP",
    ],
    answer: "C6H12O6 ---- 2CH4O3 + 4H + 2ATP",
  },
  {
    question: "The longest bone in the body is the",
    options: ["humerous", "femur", "scapula", "tibia"],
    answer: "femur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following structures is not a skeletal material?",
    options: ["Chitin", "Cartilage", "Bone", "Muscle"],
    answer: "Muscle",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The reason why the flow of blood through the capillaries is very slow is",
    options: [
      "because the walls of capillaries are very thin",
      "to avoid high blood pressure",
      "to ensure that the individual does not get dizzy",
      "to allow adequate time for exchange of materials",
    ],
    answer: "to allow adequate time for exchange of materials",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following groups of organisms has kidney as their excretory organ?",
    options: [
      "Fishes, amphibians, birds, man",
      "Fishes, amphibians, annelids, insects",
      "Fishes, reptiles, birds, tapeworms",
      "Fishes protozoans, amphibians, man",
    ],
    answer: "Fishes, amphibians, birds, man",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following features is not a characteristic of arteries?",
    options: [
      "possess values at internals throughout their length",
      "have thick muscular and elastic walls",
      "carry blood away from the heart",
      "transport oxygenated blood with the exception of the pulmonary artery",
    ],
    answer: "possess values at internals throughout their length",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The reason why hospitals use saline solutions as drip instead of water is",
    options: [
      "because salt is a preservative",
      "to prevent contamination of the body",
      "to maintain the composition of body fluids",
      "to increase the number of blood cells",
    ],
    answer: "to maintain the composition of body fluids",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The part of the ear which contains nerve cells sensitive to sound vibrations is the",
    options: ["cochlea", "ampulla", "tympanum", "malleus"],
    answer: "cochlea",
  },
  {
    question: "Spectacles with convex lenses correct long-sightedness by",
    options: [
      "converging the light rays before they enter the eye",
      "diverging the light rays before they enter the eye",
      "reducing light intensity before it enters the eye",
      "increasing light intensity before it enters the eye",
    ],
    answer: "converging the light rays before they enter the eye",
  },
  {
    question: "A seed of a flowering plant can best be described as",
    options: [
      "radicle and plumule",
      "the developed ovule",
      "the embryo and endosperm",
      "developed ovary",
    ],
    answer: "the embryo and endosperm",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following processes removes carbon from the atmosphere?",
    options: [
      "Putrefaction",
      "Photosynthesis",
      "volcanic eruption",
      "Burning fuels",
    ],
    answer: "Photosynthesis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following cycles involves the process of precipitation and transpiration?",
    options: ["Water cycles", "Carbon cycle", "Nitrogen cycle", "oxygen cycle"],
    answer: "Water cycles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the critical limiting factor for plants below the photic zone in an aquatic ecosystem?",
    options: [
      "Availability of nutrients",
      "Availability of water",
      "intensity of light",
      "Carbon dioxide concentration",
    ],
    answer: "intensity of light",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used to estimate the number of plants in a habitat?",
    options: ["Pooter", "Pitfall trap", "Quadrat", "Sweep net"],
    answer: "Quadrat",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following statements is true about sandy soil?",
    options: [
      "has limited air space",
      "is light and easy to dig",
      "drains slowly",
      "is heavy and poorly aerated",
    ],
    answer: "is light and easy to dig",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following organisms is a primary consumer?",
    options: ["Dog", "Sheep", "Grass", "Fungus"],
    answer: "Sheep",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following statements best describes the organism designated R?",
    options: [
      "feeds on S.",
      "is a primary consumer.",
      "is a producer as well as a consumer",
      "is a secondary consumer",
    ],
    answer: "is a primary consumer.",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following diseases is not hereditary?",
    options: ["Albinism", "Scabies", "Haemophilia", "Colour blindness"],
    answer: "Scabies",
  },
];
